as rivals and competitors. So Israel, who in the 1980s lobbied for and improved U.S.-Iran relations now feared a U.S.-Iran rapprochement, thinking that it would come at Israel's security interests' expense, and instead sought to put Iran in increased isolation. Ironically, this was happening at a time when Iran was more interested in peacemaking with Washington than to see to Israel's destruction. Iran had put itself in isolation because of its radicalism, and after having helped the United States indirectly in the war against Iraq in 1991, the Iranians were hoping that they would be rewarded by being included in the post-war security architecture of the region. But Washington chose to ignore Iran's outreach, as it would a decade later in Afghanistan, and instead moved to intensify Iran's isolation, and it is at this point, around 1993, '94, that Iran begins to translate its anti-Israeli ideology into operational policy. The Iranians believed that whatever they did, even if they moderated their policies, the U.S. would continue to seek Iran's isolation, and the only way Iran could compel Washington to change its position was by imposing a cost on the U.S. if it didn't. The easiest target was the peace process, and now the Iranian ideological bark was to be accompanied by a nonconventional bite, and Iran began supporting extensively Palestinian Islamist groups that it previously had shunned. In some ways, this sounds paradoxical, but according to Martin Indyk of the Clinton administration, the Iranians had not gotten it entirely wrong, because the more peace there would be between Israel and Palestine, the U.S. believed, the more Iran would get isolated. The more Iran got isolated, the more peace there would be. So according to Indyk, and these are his words, the Iranians had an interest to do us in on the peace process in order to defeat our policy of containment. To defeat our policy of containment, not about ideology. But throughout even the worst times of their entanglement, all sides have reached out to each other. Netanyahu, when he got elected in 1996, reached out to the Iranians to see if there were any ways that the doctrine of the periphery could be resurrected. Tehran was not interested. A few years later, the Iranians sent a comprehensive negotiation proposal to the Bush administration, a proposal that revealed that there was some potential of getting Iran and Israel back on terms again.
como rivales y competidores. Así, Israel, que en los '80 presionó hasta mejorar las relaciones EE.UU.-Irán ahora temía un acercamiento EE.UU.-Irán, pensando que eso sería a expensas de los intereses de seguridad de Israel y en cambio trato de confinar a Irán a un mayor aislamiento. Irónicamente, esto ocurría en un momento en el que Irán estaba más interesado en el proceso de paz con Washington que en ver la destrucción de Israel. Irán se autoaisló debido a su radicalismo, y luego de haber ayudado a Estados Unidos en forma indirecta en la guerra contra Irak, en 1991, los iraníes esperaban ser recompensados con la inclusión en la arquitectura de seguridad de la posguerra de la región. Pero Washington prefirió ignorar el acercamiento a Irán, como lo haría una década más tarde en Afganistán, y en vez de eso intensificó el aislamiento de Irán, y es en este momento, en torno a 1993, 1994, que Irán empieza a traducir su ideología anti-israelí en política operativa. Los iraníes creyeron que sin importar qué hicieran, aún si moderaban sus políticas, EE.UU. seguiría procurando el aislamiento de Irán, y la única manera en que Irán podía obligar a Washington a cambiar su postura era imponiendo un costo a EE.UU. por no hacerlo. El blanco más fácil fue el proceso de paz, y ahora el ladrido ideológico iraní iría acompañado de una mordedura no convencional, e Irán empezó a dar amplio apoyo a grupos islamistas palestinos que previamente había rechazado. En cierto modo, suena paradójico, pero para Martin Indyk, de la administración Clinton, los iraníes no lo entendieron del todo mal, dado que cuanto más paz hubiera entre Israel y Palestina, EE.UU. creía que más aislada debería estar Irán. Cuanto más aislada Irán, más paz habría. Así, para Indyk, estas son sus palabras, los iraníes tenían interés en involucrarnos en el proceso de paz para derrotar nuestra política de contención. Para derrotar nuestra política de contención, no era por ideología. Pero incluso en los peores momentos de su enredo, las partes han entrado en contacto mutuo. Cuando Netanyahu fue elegido en 1996, se puso en contacto con los iraníes para ver si había alguna manera de resucitar la doctrina de la periferia. A Teherán no le interesó. Unos años más tarde los iraníes enviaron una amplia propuesta de negociación global a la administración Bush, una propuesta que reveló que había potencial de llevar nuevamente a Irán e Israel a buenos términos.
The Bush administration did not even respond. All sides have never missed an opportunity to miss an opportunity. But this is not an ancient conflict. This is not even an ideological conflict. The ebbs and flows of hostility have not shifted with ideological zeal, but rather with changes in the geopolitical landscape. When Iran and Israel's security imperatives dictated collaboration, they did so in spite of lethal ideological opposition to each other. When Iran's ideological impulses collided with its strategic interests, the strategic interests always prevailed. This is good news, because it means that neither war nor enmity is a foregone conclusion. But some want war. Some believe or say that it's 1938, Iran is Germany, and Ahmadinejad is Hitler. If we accept this to be true, that indeed it is 1938, Iran is Germany, Ahmadinejad is Hitler, then the question we have to ask ourself is, who wishes to play the role of Neville Chamberlain? Who will risk peace? This is an analogy that is deliberately aimed at eliminating diplomacy, and when you eliminate diplomacy, you make war inevitable. In an ideological conflict, there can be no truce, no draw, no compromise, only victory or defeat. But rather than making war inevitable by viewing this as ideological, we would be wise to seek ways to make peace possible. Iran and Israel's conflict is a new phenomenon, only a few decades old in a history of 2,500 years, and precisely because its roots are geopolitical, it means that solutions can be found, compromises can be struck, however difficult it yet may be. After all, it was Yitzhak Rabin himself who said, "You don't make peace with your friends. You make it with your enemies." Thank you. (Applause)
La administración Bush ni siquiera respondió. Las partes nunca perdieron oportunidad de perder oportunidades. Pero este no es un conflicto antiguo. Ni siquiera es un conflicto ideológico. El flujo y reflujo de la hostilidad no ha cambiado por fervor ideológico, sino más bien por cambios en el panorama geopolítico. Cuando el imperativo de seguridad de Irán e Israel dictó la colaboración, así hicieron, a pesar de la letal oposición ideológica mutua. Cuando los impulsos ideológicos iraníes colisionaron con sus intereses estratégicos, siempre prevalecieron los intereses estratégicos. Estas son buenas noticias porque significa que ni la guerra ni la enemistad es una conclusión inevitable. Pero algunos quieren la guerra. Algunos creen o dicen que estamos en 1938, que Irán es Alemania, y que Ahmadinejad es Hitler. Si aceptamos que esto es cierto, que en efecto estamos en 1938, Irán es Alemania, Ahmadinejad es Hitler, entonces debemos preguntarnos: ¿Quién quiere hacer el papel de Neville Chamberlain? ¿Quién arriesgará la paz? Esta es una analogía que intenta deliberadamente eliminar la diplomacia, y cuando uno elimina la diplomacia, inevitablemente entra en guerra. En un conflicto ideológico no puede haber tregua, no hay empate, no hay punto medio, solo victoria o derrota. Pero en vez de hacer la guerra inevitable viendo esto como algo ideológico, sería conveniente encontrar maneras para hacer posible la paz. El conflicto entre Irán e Israel es un fenómeno nuevo, de unas décadas de antigüedad en una historia de 2500 años, y precisamente porque sus raíces son geopolíticas, es que pueden encontrarse soluciones, puede llegarse a puntos en común, por difícil que pueda ser. Después de todo, fue el propio Yitzhak Rabin quien dijo: "Uno no hace la paz con sus amigos. Hace la paz con sus enemigos". Gracias. (Aplausos)